[Music]
hello and welcome everyone it's active
lab live stream number 44.2
and it's may 25th 2022.
welcome to the academ lab
we're a participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference
you can find us at the links on this
slide
this is recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide feedback so we
can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
if you want to learn more about the live
streams or any other projects at active
inference lab check out
activeinference.org
okay today in 44.2 we are in our third
discussion around the paper
therapeutic alliance as octave inference
the role of therapeutic touch and
synchrony from 2022 by the authors
listed here and ian and i had a dot zero
where we contextualized and went over
some of the outline of the paper then we
had a great discussion last week with
several of the authors in the dot one
and today we're here with some of the
authors and we'll see who else joins
and we'll be continuing that discussion
around the paper we left a few threads
but also we can just take it wherever
people would like to go
and we'll begin just by
saying hello people can
say anything they want and
how is this week different than last
week
how are we approaching this paper
differently or what would we like to
resolve or
address in this dot two that
was
stimulated by the dot one or that we
didn't get to in the dot one feel free
to add anything in that area
so
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california
and
one piece in the dot 2 that i'd like to
explore would be
what are the entities
that we're discussing here
at what scales and how to think about
that in terms of their generative model
and so on
and i'll pass to ian
hello um
thank you daniel and
yes i
would like to maybe
pick up on if we've got time on the
topic of synchrony um this week and you
know what types of synchrony might be
we'd be talking about what things might
be
oscillating that come into sort of
phase lock between uh two two agents
that uh
have the potential to synchronize um
and then where do they head where do
they head towards with their synchrony
um
and then if we've got time you know
thinking about
tying this all back to the some of the
sort of core
uh
ideas about minimizing free energy and
what what does that mean for for in a
therapeutic setting
um
yes that's it i think thank you
awesome
all right any of the authors feel free
to go for it
zoe play these first
okay so uh i'm george uh i'm one of the
authors on this paper i'm an osteopath
and uh researcher and um where
you know where do i see this going
forward i pretty much enjoyed the
interaction we had last week and uh very
happy to
to kind of be left by by you guys ian
and daniel and anybody else that
want to join i think we can definitely
explore
those ideas about you know the
synchronization two agents uh and
arguably more than two agents when we
operate in a kind of not in a in a
dyadic
setting but actually a triadic setting
for example
uh pediatric care kind of elderly care
and so on we actually do
there's an act
an additional agent in in in the whole
thing so
what do i you know look forward to the
discussion um
kind of you know stimulate some ideas
about you know ways in which we can move
forward with this to the more empirical
uh states of the research
great zoe
i i'm zoe um i'm an osteopath as well
based in singapore and i'm the primary
author for this paper
um yeah happy to be led by anyone that
wants to where we want to go but
definitely happy to talk about synchrony
i think as george said it would be
important to talk about not just dyadic
but triadic or otherwise um
because i think that
adds a lot of um
depth to it but also it's easier to sort
of
discuss the effects of synchrony and
also the fact that you can be
okay lost zoe for a second
um
um anyone that wants to ask questions
okay also so is there like any other
microphone to use or could you speak
closer to the microphone
button i'm just using my laptop so that
isn't really a microphone i can take my
headphones off if that makes a
difference
it's fine it's just a little quiet but
it's fine
but
okay sorry oh no it's all it's totally
okay just want us to check okay
all right let us um
pick up with the
synchrony then
so i guess just to kind of
recall
how was this question of synchrony
approached in
the active inference literature
and maybe even outside of the active
inference literature and then how was
synchrony approached in this paper
like why was that such a core topic in
this
approach that
the authors took
um i think we started with synchrony
as the main part mainly
because when we were talking about the
therapeutic alliance um synchrony and
getting on with the other person is kind
of key and the way that we approach this
paper primarily in terms of a lot of the
aspects of how we achieve that good
therapeutic alliance was through
synchrony so that's kind of where we
um that's one of the reasons
through active inference
it was also
about we started i started the research
when i was looking at it right from
sort of the start and
looking at how
communication worked and how why people
would want to sort of synchronize
together and why people
to implement active inference into sort
of the structure that we had
it was important to kind of see why
that would be beneficial because we
wanted to use or
we like to say that the synchrony
enables us to work together to then
therefore um save free energy be more
efficient and then
that's how we kind of
we we very much used it to apply the
this active influence
sort of framework around
around it um and so
i felt that it was very key
without the synchrony element it would
be very
it was kind of the backbone into which a
lot of the effects of um active
influence in the way that we achieve
therapeutic alliance seem to sort of
center around without that connection
between different people
um we wouldn't be we wouldn't be able to
be to save energy to work together to
have a better relationship with our
practitioners we wouldn't um with the
patients and practitioners we would be
able to get the
clinical applications and benefits from
it
so
i saw synchrony as sort of the key
to sort of get to where the
sort of paper was so it was sort of a
key concept um
to use in order to implement it all
together
uh george
um
yeah um
but so when we when we started the
project actually um
kind of putting some ideas along the
lines um of how could we apply
predictive processing and the free
energy active inference within
australia and within the the osteopathic
setting
um
synchrony came along actually after um
the super
initial discussion with carl frist and
that
kind of suggested this it's actually
you know look into this stuff because it
actually could be
quite a robust way of of you know of
understanding uh
what goes on in the in in the clinic
room uh when two people are working
together with a specific kind of aim
there is a little bit of literature
in psychotherapy
kind of demonstrating that actually the
therapeutic alliance
becomes
much more robust uh when two people
synchronize
and
both at the kind of um
you know behavioral but also
well
biological level and
and it was nothing about sort of okay
you know this is about pure verbal
communication non-verbal but
primarily by kind of copying body
movements and so on um to think okay you
know how can this be applied in the
context of actually uh
an approach that is largely hands-on
based you know the manual
therapy so that's where it kind of
started from it was one way of
of trying like like zoe said kind of
looking at through patrick alliance
when people interact um
to try and understand what goes on in
the dyadic setting
kind of two people but also a little bit
beyond that you know it kind of what
happens when there's actually more
people involved in that therapeutic
relationship that need to be consulted
need to be involved in the process and
so on and so
that's that was the kind of early stage
and
yeah and then we we thought that
actually this is a good way of of of
understanding
um
a little bit more about how we can
create the conditions of developing a
strong kind of a
ecological niche that is based on that
synchrony of that sort of understanding
of that
give and take like a little bit like we
talked about last week the kind of the
bird song you know
people taking turns kind of
understanding listening okay
acting kind of taking on go back and so
on and that's sort of in a sense like
a kind of a a nice wave that goes back
and forth but it is a kind of very nice
and tranquil kind of a wave
another one that just crashes and
destroys everything but actually one way
you know one step kind of goes on
a little bit like the pendulum kind of
uh
analogy once you introduce that nice
pendulum kind of things
happen
that's where we sort of thought you know
it
could be one way of exploring the
the whole process of care
thank you ian
thank you so um
yeah you know i'm fascinated by the the
topic of synchrony and
the the little bits i've read in the
literature about how
um you know measurable things that might
be able to synchronize between one or
two or more people so you know daniel i
think we discussed this in the dot zero
so
um
choirs singing together
they have been shown their their their
hearts rates kind of synchronize with
their breathing
um
and
i think in the paper there was some
records are cited for similar sort of
stuff in drama group drumming circles
for example so so that really interests
me and i can kind of begin to see how
in a therapeutic setting that kind of
synchrony could lead someone um who's
maybe stressed and anxious into a kind
of more
um
healthy
uh increase their parasympathetic
activity and
that is conducive to healing um
then but i've also got these other sort
of nagging things about synchrony as
well
that uh
um maybe i touched on in in the you know
the the dot
zero which is what are we synchronizing
towards and is it always you know
um
beneficial so you know
this this kind of
the
less kind of lockstep synchrony that you
talked about daniel um
so maybe it's just um
you know let's say a child saying mummy
mommy mommy waving their arms around and
then the mum synchronize they
synchronize their attention together so
you get mother and child and then
then you've got a choice so there's some
aspect that's synchronized you know that
i think in the paper it talks about the
arms and you know the limbs and the the
voice kind of synchronizing but you know
and the facial expressions but um
you know a caregiver might then
lead the child to a soothing kind of
parasympathetic
way soothe it or it might say you know
give it a clip behind the air and say
you know children has to be seen and not
heard and
try and stop the attention you know the
attention is synchronized but the
the um
the action
may not be therapeutic so
um
yeah i'm just sort of thinking about
where
you know where
just because something's synchronized
does it mean it's always minimizing
free energy or just because
it's uh
you know things in the therapeutic world
go in and out of fashion so
frontal lobotomy is okay we don't do
that anymore but that for a while there
was some kind of synchronized thinking
in the therapeutic world that that's a
good idea for people and
you know i
there are ideas that i hear
in the wider kind of therapy world that
are fashionable
but um and they're being applied um but
you know they
in 50 years time
we may look that they may have been
leading people away from minimizing free
energy or men or improving health so
um yeah
they're my thoughts
okay awesome yeah a lot there george
um
i think the interesting thing you know
is
there are nagging questions there for
sure um
the first one do we always synchronize
and uh you know when if you don't
synchronize what we're gonna do
because you know clearly there are cases
where
we know the therapeutic relationship is
going nowhere okay
we can say whatever you know we can try
our best but actually
there is resistance to change from the
patients we
end up not understanding each other
and uh you know arguably that's a
relationship that will not evolve
and well you might even get to a point
at the end you know maybe the good idea
to go and see a colleague of mine kind
of thing okay
so
do we synchronize with everybody no
clearly not
is there any value understanding this
stuff by sometimes understanding there's
some kind of
gestures and sort of body language and
so on um
voice sound sort of communication style
we're probably uh giving us cues to
maybe to adapt a little bit
so to try and synchronize a little bit
better i think that that's useful i
think important
in order to be a good communicator i
think
first and foremost you know sometimes
people worry too much about the
technical skills and the ability of
doing x and y and doing some some
miracles and so on arguably you know
what the first thing that people need to
be in a clinical setting is a good
communicator
and a pretty good nice person okay and i
think you know if that's if that's there
i think
we we've got we create the conditions
and good communicators likely to
to have potentially better outcomes that
guys that
basically don't care and sort of they're
the experts and so on
the other question is you know is it
always about minimizing free energy
because you know there are situations
um
where probably you know you want to
short circuit the whole thing isn't it
you want to sort of flatten a little bit
of that sort of sensory states you know
you want to create
a condition where and the only way you
can you can
you can sort of uh
change the generative model is actually
by creating a massive surprise
a massive prediction error that
arguably surprises the system in a way
like wow what just happened you know
and actually oh okay
so it's i don't think it's always about
minimizing free energy as is not
but sometimes i think you know you want
to shock the whole thing because the
system on the other side wants to
minimize free energy for sure
you know if you mine
if i'm a kind of chronic pain patient
and i you know i'm scared of moving and
you tell me to move and so on the
reaction is you know i anticipate the
the likelihood of movement leading to
pain i anticipate the consequences of
actions in the future the typical active
inference
model and you know lock i don't move so
i probably want to short circuit the
whole thing just to create a condition
where you know it's actually okay to
move
because it's not going to cause any harm
and so
is it through synchrony
um
maybe it isn't okay
so i think i i think that's not a sort
of i think um
a kind of one-size-fits-all kind of
thing uh and i don't think you know it's
just about sort of always that
minimizing free energy because i think
creating change that is meaningful
change
uh probably needs a little bit more of
he needs to
he needs to destroy that sort of strong
fire kind of thing so i can
implant another chip kind of thing yeah
in a metaphorical way
and that's why we know in in some
mental health conditions why some types
of of drugs like ketamine and so on
create that condition you know that
you know
sort of zeros the whole thing is a bit
like you know you reset the button isn't
it the computer is stuck what you do
you've tried everything you unplug the
computer and then you try again the
whole thing reboots isn't it so i think
sometimes that's the that's the analogy
of what maybe what we want to
achieve in the setting is it through
synchrony
i personally i i don't know and i'm not
entirely sure
i think if you
of course if the people started
understanding each other then that
creates the conditions for this thing
probably to happen because if i if you
don't understand me as a practitioner i
don't understand you as a patient it's
pretty hard that actually i
i create the conditions to change so
maybe it's through synchrony but again
you know
as a sort of big question marks really
so
thanks so just yes zoe please
yeah so i think um going off what george
said yes i think i mean overall the goal
would be to minimize free energy but to
it
to be able to do that you have to sort
of
at some point challenge it right you're
not gonna have the same belief that you
think is the most efficient
when you're born to when you die
the way that you become
used like reduce
energy is going to change over time
you'll see that especially in sort of
pediatrics you see it in sports um
there's a lot of studies with running
for example that show that the more you
run the more often the more mileage that
people do when they run the more
efficient they get so
i think free energy is
yes we all want to reduce it but at some
point we've got to update it and
challenge it right so
it won't be sort of just this linear
thing where you're constantly just
changing it you've got to update it and
challenge it at some point so it will
sort of be a little bit of a
a roller coaster and have a few dips
where you've got to take that risk
to see if there's another way that is
more efficient and that will save it
more um
whether synchrony
is always necessary i'm not sure i think
i definitely think
that
when you're unsure whether
or if your
prior is not so precise and you're not
100 sure that that is the
best way to do whatever you're doing or
you're not 100 certain that your belief
is
explains what's going on then i think
you're more likely to synchronize with
others i think
you
once you're quite certain on what you
think and what you're going to do then
it's a lot harder to
synchronize like with the cognitive sort
of immunity when you've got chronic pain
it's a lot harder to change that
because you're convinced that you're
you're right you've had this pain for
years maybe and you know what it's like
if you
bend forward it's gonna hurt so why
would you bother to challenge that um
it's i think
yeah i think there's a lot of studies
that show that especially with sort of
babies that they synchronize with their
as they once they when they're younger
the synchrony is is very consistent
um obviously they need to to work with
their caregiver to get their
static needs and everything that they
need to keep surviving but
it shows that they do still think when
they're adults but the time when they're
older or in adulthood that they do think
is when they're unsure with when you
know something happens and you are near
that caregiver and you you don't you
don't know you still sort of
rely on on them say i don't know you get
into a car accident or something um and
there's a big shock and you're not sure
you often the child will still no matter
how old they are will look to the to the
parent um
obviously unless the the parent is very
elderly but generally speaking in times
of uncertainty you will look towards
someone else
um so i think
it's equally always necessary you know
but i think if you're
not 100 certain with your priors and you
are questioning it or there is a doubt
of that questioning it then i think
synchrony will play more of a role
in it
and i'll talk about that
awesome thanks yeah just thinking about
beliefs in the
way that we might talk about them
hey blue welcome just the way that we
might conversationally talk about
beliefs
if somebody is unsure about something
that's when they look to be synchronized
by some other informational resource i'm
not sure what time this thing opens so
i'm going to look it up in this way or
i'm going to ask this person or i'm not
sure where to go so i'm going to follow
the crowd we see that kind of in the ant
pheromone trail we see that in the
social media
all these different areas and then
conversely when somebody does have a
more confident
more built up prior
then
that's more like going their own way and
potentially
being more resistant to
external contrasting information and
then translating from that one
conversational meaning of belief like i
believe that is going to open at this
time
into
a broader bayesian perspective
on bayesian brain and body and like
thinking about pain and perception
as also
parameters that are can be seen as
as beliefs
in this bayesian sense so not always
like a psychological experienced belief
but in some statistical way it's like
they're held stances
that are updated in some way or
partially or completely by certain kinds
of incoming information so
ian and then also like this is going to
be i think very
interesting to
return to the free energy minimization
and unpack like what we mean by free
energy there so ian go for it
uh thanks so um
yeah i'm just sort of wanting to check
that um
some of the language used in other
realms of uh therapy so this idea of
self-regulation and co-regulation
um are we are we saying here that this
um synchrony
for in therapeutic reliance is a form of
co-regulation um
that that we hear a lot about in uh
you know people um with disorder
um
problems with their autonomic nervous
system and then we say we you go to a
therapist to help co-regulate your
autonomic nervous system is that what
we're saying is synchrony is the kind of
mechanism
for co-regulation
which
i believe fits with what you're saying
zoe that children need that more and as
adults we might do that occasionally
and um then i'm just thinking also you
know other forms of therapeutic
synchrony and co-regulation so meeting
friends for a coffee
uh sometimes
um
you know i might be having a bit of a
stressful week or
or a uh
a wobble in some way and then i meet
some friends and we kind of uh
um seek counselling each other have a
synchronize our
movement of our hands to our mouth with
a coffee cup or listen to some music
together tap our feet together and
that's a kind of um
therapeutic so are we all kind of
doing this on and off all the time um
they're my thoughts or questions
yes george
zoe then george
um yeah no i just wanted to say yes with
the
co-regulation i think that we kind of
not always but i think we do add an
element to try and suggest that um we'd
like to say that we in part help
co-regulation and co
we as a as a practitioner to achieve
sort of recovery and and reduce pain and
um and how we
i think we all want to say that we help
in that process and that we help
regulate their sort of destructive
pattern whether that's inflammation
whether that's pain
um whatever sort of metrics that you
want to
um
rate your your treatment by or whatever
your treatment goals are that you're
sort of working towards i think we all
want to say that we sort of
help
regulate what um
which ways we regulate in terms of where
there are sort
of um we actually change that their
heart rate or
um things like that we haven't got sort
of
we're not always so specific about or we
don't have the research to kind of show
that but we
i think certainly there is elements of
sympathetic and parasympathetic things
that that we do
as well as sort of the intent to
co-regulate even if we
don't sort of empirically do it
um or achieve it whether just that
reassurance that we're attempting to
help
um regulate their their pain um
i think is sort of the intention that i
hope that as a practitioner i am giving
off to my my patients and i'll let
george speak
um
i think you know um
if we see you know if you come from a
a manual therapy background a touch
based hands-on approach
uh one could argue or old-school kind of
beliefs in the profession christine
osteopathy would would argue that
actually
how you achieve that core
co-regulation um you know autonomic
nervous system synchronic
parasympathetic is primarily through the
use of techniques you know you use a
technique in a particular part of the
body and this affects
uh you know the parasympathetic part and
so on okay the vagus nerve and all that
stuff that that sort of
implies there is a tool that by which
you can apply that stuff treat that
particular bit and buy miracle you know
modulate everything
um i used to be there no longer there
because you know the evidence isn't
isn't strong enough to actually
support those clients
on the other hand if we add another
element which is the element in the the
synchrony
and the synchrony here goes beyond just
that sort of passive
uh
practitioner type of intervention into
something that implies communication
implies uh alignment you know attuning
to this to the environment and the
environment there is the practitioner as
well
so the other person in the room the the
guy that is facilitating the process so
sort of takes us i think away from
this idea that you know everything is
about touches everything about the
manual stuff and so on but it becomes a
kind of um a multi-pronged approach
where touch matters that communication
matters as much as touch
and it's not a technique x y or z but
it's actually the whole package of care
that's likely to to enable us to to get
there
so
you know is it similar to you know and
and i kind of uh you know i like your
analogy to sort of you know tough day
and so on you go out you need to see
your friends you need to synchronize in
a different environment because
ultimately people you know will talk
talk to each other and coral regulate
each other even in terms of reducing our
static load of a tough week and so on um
there are kind of things that that are
similar to what happens in the clinical
setting one of them we're probably
thinking about reward systems as well
you know there's a there's a sort of a
participation in something that is
likely to
even if uncomfortable is left it's going
to lead to some improvement it kind of
you know maybe
maybe there's some dopamine stuff there
maybe there is a reward pathways that
are
kind of involved in the whole thing like
having a drink in the same having a
therapeutic intervention that
ultimately is going to
get me to to a better state
i think it's very very analogous to
moving away from the free energy
principle and to an area that is
kind of uh
works alongside that in activism um
the concept of sense making you know
so
the kind of
and uh
what inactivists would argue participate
three sense making
so synchrony could be
and also looked from that from that lens
from that perspective
whereas the two people or more than two
people either in a group you know having
a drink and all kind of helping each
other because i listen and or in a
therapeutic setting that's sort of
participatory things making uh
minimizing free energy or to puyses for
the the kind of the inactivists and it's
actually i think you know we we
we sort of uh
looking at the same phenomena maybe with
different language but arguably the same
kind of phenomena so you
say i think it's that package that
probably helps core regulation rather
than just
one
one intervention
thank you
blue
welcome
do you want to
add anything or ask anything
uh not right off the bat just hi it's
nice to be here with you guys i'm sorry
i missed last week and i've really
enjoyed the discussions with the paper
so far and
um i'll jump in in a little bit i think
you guys were engrossed in a in a good
conversation so
okay awesome so the dopamine angle and a
few other things let's we'll return to
but we were talking about minimizing
free energy
and i wanted to
show a few images from the textbook
because even those who have seen free
energy come up in a lot of different
settings
sometimes returning to the basics is
a generator that helps us take it in
many other ways and for those who are
maybe focused more on the clinical
setting or have more of that background
this can provide a little
uh
you know other tissues around the
connective tissue free energy is being
used like a connective tissue here it's
bridging a lot of different ideas it's
helping us connect different sensory
modalities and therapeutic modalities
so just a few
cool images from the active inference
textbook
so here is
figure um 2.3
and it's the action perception loop
and the two ways that discrepancies
related to predictions or expectations
the two ways that discrepancies about
observations can be reduced
just qualitatively is through changing
belief
and changing action
and it's some blend of those two that
individual entities are engaged in in
this action perception loop
and then
when we're specifically talking about
free energy
there's some type of
equation
this is like a simple form of it
that is going to
make that discrepancy minimization
[Music]
tractable and possible to calculate
for
at least us doing statistics from
outside the system if not for the system
itself to do
and what is the real sort of
um
hidden goal is this minimization of true
surprise
but the minimization of true surprise
is intractable or it's inaccessible
and so free energy
serves as like this upper bound whereas
if we can reduce
this upper bound
we're getting implicitly closer
to this
asymptotic reduction of some pr of
surprise
so
who's doing this reduction of surprise
that relates to the entity
um question what is the entity that's
actually doing free energy minimization
and so
what are the entities that we're talking
about here
what
does it mean to minimize free energy
and when is it
and and i i
liked how earlier it was brought up when
sometimes where that free energy
minimization was going with the flow and
then sometimes when there was a flow
disrupt so what is free energy
minimization and what are the entities
and how are we modeling that ian and
then anyone else
thanks um yeah that question of what are
the entities and um linking it back to
george's point about sense making and
inactivism so
um
in the paper there was um some really
interesting stuff on um the
realizing that we're all alike
um
in the therapeutic alliance and
relating that back to
sense making i'm thinking that you know
therapeutically or meeting threat you
know in a in a manual therapy or meeting
friends there's you know the outcome
might be ah
i'm not a weirdo i'm not you know i'm
not i haven't done anything wrong
everything's okay again
um i'm relaxed and
that's therapeutic so you know i'm
amongst people who are very much alike
me um and that's the sense-making
there's the pattern recognition you know
i'm a valuable member of my tribe
however you want to describe it
um
and then i think you know
how
but we're not we're never completely
identical
um or are we i don't know
uh
so
the proposal in the paper is that that's
the ultimate realization that we're all
alike and i can kind of see that that's
a kind of relieving thing to realize
um
but
you know we're similar but we're
in am i i'm similar to my pet dog in
that i've got eyes and
i breathe and my heart beats and i can
synchronize in some ways with that and
it feels nice but my dog can't help me
do my accounts for example um
so
yes
this this likeness and um
how does that fit into sense making
thanks blue
so as i've been reading the textbook
i've been um thinking a lot about the
hidden states and it's interesting to
think about that in terms of using touch
to kind of resolve uncertainty about the
hidden states
because while a state might be hidden to
the patient right when you present with
some like i've got a pain in my shoulder
or something like that um
it might be easy for the therapist to
say oh that's this this and i push here
and tweak this and then it's better um
but like so it might be hidden to the
patient but not hidden to the doctor or
hit into the doctor
and the patient or hit into
the
patient but not the doctor or the doctor
but not the patient so it might be like
all of these things and so it's like
working together this kind of synchrony
to resolve uncertainty about about a
hidden state and i've i've thought a lot
about like who's making the observation
um and who's who's doing the state
observing
uh and who is the state hidden to and
and it brings back what um the paper
that you guys mentioned in the dot zero
the communication as active inference
because it really is like a
bi-directional
um harmonious kind of thing happening
right
awesome
thanks yes
george
um
yeah
so um actually starting with the hidden
states
who's observing who's been observed i
think
uh
you know the free energy model or
picture the typical representation with
the two agents and or one agent in the
world and
internal states external states and so
on so if you have the two agents you
know there's something in the middle
that clearly is the ground where
we kind of
try to achieve some form of alignment
and then
um
that certainly implies the reading of
someone else's
internal state
uh i think you know that who makes the
observation who's been observed and so
on i think again it is is the bird song
is a given take because
they are clearly situations where
you may be telling your patient that
actually is nothing to worry about
for example where you're not
particularly
sure about what's going on and the
patient can clearly read
in your body language that
no it's um is is hiding something from
me right
it's it's it's something there that
doesn't feel right
and and actually um
there's an interesting phenomena for
example with in chronic conditions um
which is the concept of
uh cognitive immunization where um
it's very common these days for
you know
patient goes and sees a practitioner has
read has consulted with dr google to
start dr google said you know it could
be x y and z typically the worst case
scenario goes and sees
uh
doctor number one doctor number one says
yeah you know what you know it's nothing
to worry about there's nothing wrong
with you depression has got pain kind of
saying all right i don't trust you kind
of thing
then goes and sees partition and number
two that comes with a different story
and yeah okay maybe you forget about you
forgotten about something goes to
practitioner number three and so on and
gets through a process where
authors argue that it's a kind of you
know
the system becomes
cognitively immune to any new
explanations because
the expectation is surely there's
something wrong with me so clearly in
those conditions you know if we take
from this lens
one could argue uh yeah as a patient i'm
observing you i'm kind of reading your
internal states which is i don't trust
you kind of thing because you're
actually telling me something but
actually
something that potentially you don't
believe either okay or you know this
thing about let's do cognitive
reassurance because
most non-specific backbone or neck pain
you know one cannot say that's clearly a
particular tissue responsible for
the pain
the symptoms and so on so you say okay
you know
there's nothing serious with you so
what's wrong with me you know you
clearly can't tell the patient oh you've
got non-specific back pain because for
the patient that means you haven't got a
clue about what's wrong with me or
you're implying that something upstairs
in my head i'm making it up so
patients observe us for sure and they
know when we
kind of are confident and so on and when
we
we're not so confident and maybe we're
not entirely sure if actually the whole
thing is going to happen in the same way
we observe patients
we
we start observing them you know when
they come through the door
when you first greet them and so on hi
how are you doing before kobe times you
know shaking hands and so on were a
pretty good first kind of getting into
someone else's internal state
because just the you know the
the handshake the quality of the the
amount of pressure the confidence and so
on in a lot of you know there were cases
say this person is anxious this person
is down he's depressed and so on and he
could get that uh down to
you know when you clinic do clinical
examination you touch you observe you
you feel you palpate and so on so
um
that implies that there's a lot of
unconscious stuff that
it's
you know
it's process
comes through arrives through our
our sensory our sensorian and uh you
know we made something
out of it so i think that that's what we
kind of um
you know one of the things we're trying
to explore
through this stuff about you know
try to understand someone else's
internal
state you know predicting a little bit
of their mental state
and uh
and that's where synchrony and that's
where alignment
um kind of plays that important role
because you know there's no alignment i
can't clearly guess what's wrong
going on um the stuff about you know
what what you
and what you mentioned about sense
making and so on
sense making is is quite an interesting
thing and you said okay you know
we're not like
you know
a patient is a patient and the
practitioner is a practitioner you know
there is that
power differential as well you know
there's the doctor there's the patient
uh when one is an expert and when the
other is an expert
and things alternate
and
the the whole thing about sense making
and actually minimization of free energy
and so on since making is quite an
interesting thing to
when we look at some
clinical conditions and there's some
beautiful stuff written about for
example mental health and um
inactive approaches and
looking at for example depression as a
disorder of sense making for example uh
and you see that
sometimes with patients with chronic
musculoskeletal problems
that also have
you know a comorbidity they have
depression what came first the
depression of the back or the back pain
one could argue that um
if i suffer from chronic back pain and i
can't get out of the house i can't see
my friends i can't walk my dog i can't
play with my children and so on
the world stops kind of making sense
right
you know i don't go out because outside
is a is a cruel world and it's kind of
full of you know
dangers and so on so i stay in a safe
environment which is my home watching
telly
kind of uh you know complaining about
myself to myself
okay
and uh and i become depressed because
i'm stuck look
so
um
the therapeutic real you know the the
therapeutic encounter that sort of uh
nice ecological niche in a sense
creates opportunity for sense making
to to understand where there's patterns
for example rigid behavior
rigid thinking that actually
by uh understanding by uh interacting i
can potentially start sort of taking the
patient in a particular direction
which is the sort of you know
this kind of road to recovery
uh
and one you know i one could argue that
if someone starts feeling um
kind of bettering themselves
symptoms reduce a little bit can start
doing a little bit more can start again
engaging with the world
maybe the other stuff about feeling
miserable
would get better as well and i think
that's that's sometimes what we see in
musculoskeletal care is this stuff you
know we don't treat mental health
conditions and i don't think we should
make those claims because they're
clearly
you know
boundaries and competences and so on but
but you know the patient that has got
for example a chronic musculoskeletal
problem and gets better
and gets an impact you know that impact
changes their quality of life changes
their ability to
you know become an agent again because
pain
they lost their agency because of pain
i think that's where the the kind of the
beauty of this understanding this stuff
kind of comes is you know you can impact
on some you know on different levels of
the person of the self
that is clearly not just that
in body itself that body but it's beyond
that embodied itself is the sort of you
know this multi-dimensional kind of um
what is to be a person kind of thing
right and
so yeah and i think that sometimes it's
about
kind of reading the others the you know
understanding the other guy's internal
state
is about sort of
doing the right thing at the right time
because i know there's there's a cue
that tells me maybe i if i do this stuff
this could be really
you know one way of getting in
surprising the system in a very positive
way
okay so
i've just been participating so
joey
[Music]
yes uh
yeah i think
oh gosh let me take my hand down okay
yeah i think similar to what george said
on sort of it's uh a bird song i think
there's different aspects where
you know
yes generally on the the technical the
physiology or the anatomy side then the
practitioner is always obviously more
the expert but i think there's certain
things where maybe you're looking at a
patient or you're you know still trying
to examine them and
the
the patient is still going to be the
expert in their pain and so you
you might be tossing and turning between
a few diagnoses say and then the patient
suddenly comes up with like oh yeah by
the way
and then what you were thinking
completely goes out so i think you
completely read them
um there's always going to be sort of
hidden states that you don't know about
and then you kind of have to you're
always on the lookout in case the
situation is changing or
maybe they don't want to tell you
exactly what it is and you're not you
you think something's missing that
intuition that maybe there's an element
of this that you're not that you're not
getting or suddenly they got worse and
you're wondering well what happened like
what changed what
what what goes on and then you find out
that you know um
their child's been really sick or
something or their work's been really
stressful or something else has happened
excluding that they haven't said that
you kind of pick up on
um
so i think there's there's that where
you kind of you're inferring what that
other person
means and there's definitely
you know you're watching them they're
watching you
and you're kind of still you know
deciding what's going to happen based on
the sort of what you think is going on
and
and that and throughout treatment
you know there's no set treatment for
certain things as well like whether it's
exercises or
touch you
have to adapt based on what you're
feeling
and similarly to what you
um think it's the ian that brought it up
um
before the sort of synchrony and whether
it's exact or not well
it sort of also depends on the stimulus
there's a lot of
research that
um there was one paper that
was about a film
and um
they got two separate people
to watch the same film
um
in by themselves at at separate times
but in certain parts of the the film
their heart rate was exactly the same
um
their heart rate went up when
you know the fight scene happened and
then their heart when it went down the
same and actually you know the
difference was they were in sync even
though they
were
nowhere near each other couldn't see
each other didn't know what that person
was doing they're probably doing
completely different things but the
stimulus
dictated the synchrony
um so i think that's an interesting
thing
to um
[Music]
to consider as well that the synchrony
might be from
from the stimulus that's happening
during the treatment whether it's touch
whether it's something else but we
focused on touch but
yeah the
whether you synchronize just based on
what you're
in in that moment um
but actually you know it's completely
different otherwise so
um
yeah i just wanted to point out
thanks that that reminds me a lot of
this direct
interfacing
mechanism of synchrony which might be
via like auditory communication
touch and so on and then there's this
more stigmergy
based
niche modification
construction of a niche like a corn maze
where everybody walking through it is
having a shared experience or like you
said with two people watching the same
film it's like there's some
similarity in their niche
and so there's
um a resulting synchronization
without direct interfacing because
they're interacting in a shared
there's something shared about their
niche either two people going through
the same niche at different moments
patients coming through a space
or there's people that are
in separate physical spaces but the
niche has some similarity
and i'm sure there's a lot of other
examples like that um
ian and then i have that image up if you
want to describe what you
wanted to share
there thanks daniel uh yeah i will we'll
describe that in a moment but as uh um
the conversation about films i'm just
thinking that
hollywood and filmmakers are actually
masters of uh
inducing synchrony really you know
they've got the bird song so they've got
the
the beautiful music or the dramatic
music or whatever you've got the imagery
the words the the com composition of the
images to hopefully not obviously not
everyone will have the same experience
of a film but they hope that their sad
film will
induce some synchrony amongst the
viewers in terms of the
response in their body or a happy film
will induce some kind of
rhythmic laughter um
so uh
yeah and uh i'm thinking about some work
i've um
heard of recently of uh john viveki
looking at emotional goosebumps
um
and
how this links to um
he thinks it's uh the process of
temperature regulation is being exacted
up into um
some kind of
relevance
things salient to us through
goosebumps um
and there's an opportunity there to kind
of open up cognitively and explore some
other ideas that maybe
the person wasn't able to before and you
can think okay that music gave me
goosebumps and i had all these ideas um
so yeah there's just a few things as we
were talking there that i was thinking
about but um this diagram was george as
you were talking about the kind of how
you know the complex things that um
might be at play
with in the patient this was um done by
mit i only found out about it a few days
ago it was 2015
but all of these different factors that
might lead someone into a kind of um
vicious cycle of depression and you know
we've got things like
uh
cortisol or unreg you know unbridled
inflammation at the top there but then
you've also got as you said george the
physical inactivity and how this you've
got all these different looping
perception
action cycles here that are
creating this sort of downward spiral
and you know therapeutically i guess
what we're trying to do is create an
upward opening
trying to get an access point and you
know zoe you said you might have to try
lots of things i have to try looking
trying one of these loops and if that
doesn't work okay
try a different loop to
open up this sort of thing that's
tightening and maybe open it up
either physically or
perceptually
yeah thank you this is like very much
showing that complex causation and so
sometimes a disciplinary approach
um might be like well hippocampal volume
is associated with this change
and that could absolutely be empirically
true or cytokine signaling or early
adverse experiences
and so
part of the challenge is reassembling
this complex causal network
and then even
if there were some sort of causal
network that could be reassembled
then how
might the
failure mode
be similar or different from the
recovery mode like there are certain
things that cannot be
changed like in the past and there's
other things
kind of like the concept of hysteresis
where
we can't just
reversibly modify something and so where
are the leverage points in this
diagram
and it's yeah
george
um
yeah it's
pretty complex but yeah
very good very good diagram for sure and
i think you know that
there's a lot of stuff that we
you know we are talking about that's
clearly there
um
i think you know where you know clearly
we have
you know we have modifiable and
non-modifiable things you know
the kind of uh there's stuff you know we
can't change someone else someone else's
genetics we can't change you know what
happened in the past okay
but they are modifiable things that's uh
at least in uh
in the context of musculoskeletal care
um
you know are are present you know that
can include
beliefs you know their prayers about you
know their ideas about pain and what's
wrong with them and so on down to things
that uh could be lifestyle okay and
and lifestyle
yeah it could be more movements uh
kind of changing the diet or whatever
stop smoking kind of engaging in
something that
starts getting them kind of uh you know
start getting the their sense making
back okay
um
through the sense you know that the
ideas that actually
where uh the other the other interesting
thing about this stuff you know where
are the opportunities
you know how can we start
how can we start
that process of change
a very nice model
typically align more with inactivist
approach now sort of finding ways into
pain and so on are the ecological
psychology ideas about the fortune
affordances
you know what's outside what is out
there in the environment
you know already linked you know some
some authors to kind of the active
inference predictive processing and so
on but
clearly one can think about you know
the world provides us with with the
landscape of of affordances you know
stuff that
uh
kind of uh are our opportunities for
action which is basically what the
description of an affordance is and one
that lives in a very nice environment
for example with a beautiful park and
can walk you know along the coastline
and uh you know stress-free environment
and so on clearly that that world
it's a world for a sort of you know
beautiful kind of lifestyle and so on
right whereas if one lives in an urban
urban jungle and everybody's super
stressed outside and so on arguably that
landscape
kind of is much
much smaller and you know when we we say
yeah you know would be good for you to
start walking for example you know that
would be a good way of start to start
managing your back pain the patient can
say yeah but you know when i get out of
the house i'm i'm struggling i might
just get
run over by a car straight away
the environment outside is is awful you
know there's pollution everywhere you
know what do you want me to do you know
kind of uh
yeah i i'm scared of going outside so no
thank you very much because of course if
you are on the other
side of the of the spectrum and you can
invite the person and use what's up
there and start playing a little bit
with those opportunities for action um
i think that's
those are tools that if you think
sometimes you know we can start thinking
very hard about what sort of exercises
should the patient do
should the person get engaged and so on
and if we think much you know in much
simpler terms and think about you know
what's outside what's out there what
kind of you know what kind of things are
already in the environment that can be
used
to actually
promote change uh you know we would be
surprised that actually just the flight
of stairs would be good enough you know
don't take the lift take the stairs and
um you know
start sort of uh walking a little bit
back and forth you know from home to
work and so on those minimal things if
the person feels like yeah okay i'll
have a go and i'll try that
clearly we are in a in that process of
you know uh
change uh kind of changing a little bit
of their
their sort of internal state you know
maybe that prior about
yeah i can't move i can't lift because
you know it'll damage my back in fact
when they
start trusting their bodies um you know
they can do a little bit more so
there's a kind of uh it's always hard to
think about okay how can i change this
how can i change the the generative
model and we almost think you know
everything needs to be
conscious cognitive and so on when in
fact
a lot of stuff happens unconsciously
right
you know
if it was always about i'm going to
think about changing and i'm going to do
this and
then the the world would be much simpler
right but you know we you know so a lot
of stuff is hidden anyway and even the
person is not aware of that stuff so
but
so so the change the process the tools
and so on i kind of
this is a facet you know that goes back
to that
very good diagram with all these factors
and i think as a practitioner yes okay i
can focus entirely on the brain and the
neuroscience of it and become like a
brain-centric approach or i can start
thinking about actually the brain is you
know it's the hardware kind of stuff
but there's much more in it and much
more in it
takes the person takes the environment
takes the kind of opportunities and so
on the stuff out there can be used
thank you george zoe
yeah just going off of what um george
said in terms of um the environment
around it like when you're sort of
maybe if you're surrounded by nature or
things like that then you might be sort
of more willing or more
able to change your priors i think it's
also important to realize especially
through touch that it's one
mortality right it's one way in which
we're starting to kind of try to
understand and try to
to manipulate the process of sort of
changing those memories um whether it's
the way it's
processed or just having
initially or just trying to adapt it and
that's that touch
is one way but
i think also it's
interesting that it's probably more
likely that we may not be able to
completely change that sort of
uh prior but we might in that context
so we might not change the fact that
it's painful to bend down but we might
be able to
through touch and through sort of
treatment
get the
patient to realize okay well yes maybe
bending forwards is is dangerous it is
it's a bad thing but
if you do it in a certain way and you
look at it in this way then actually
it's not so bad
so
i think it's it's yeah it's in it it's
important to take the context into it i
think
with with this i think we might be able
to maybe not completely change the the
maladaptive belief but with touch we can
try to change it so that it's more
context specific rather than a general
belief that isn't able to change we
might be able to change it so in certain
circumstances whether it's the way we do
things or just the way that we approach
things we might be able to
update it or modify it for that specific
thing
um
i know the papers were talking about it
in terms of like being scared of spiders
you know you might still be scared of
spiders but if you know that you're
scared of spiders and they've got food
nearby and they're despite as happy then
maybe the other spider's still scary but
it's not likely to kill you
um or something like that in this
circumstance it's not as bad as it it
could be and you're going to be safe
um from whatever sort of fear it is so i
think
that's
an important thing to add on from what
george was saying and i'll pause it back
to george
yes george and then ian
uh
now this is you know
what's always just sense kind of uh
yeah it's quite quite important and we
know through touch we can clearly
get in kind of
effect
understanding and so on
um i think that that's
all the positive stuff about touch
there's another factor another side of
the equation which i think you know as
practitioners we need to be aware of
which is
the power of you know
what's the hidden state and that touch
can trigger
and
particularly when in trauma situations
memories are embodied and when you touch
someone in a particular part of the body
that might again bring that unconscious
stuff about for example someone has been
a victim of sexual abuse for example
and you could touch a person and
straight away
uh either there is a sort of an you know
a massive
response
you know fight or flight you know what's
going on here uh or you might actually
um if it is about this sort of hidden
states
uh you might actually find that you know
that touch kind of created a response
that is almost like a no-go zone and you
kind of need to be aware that sometimes
you know you touch people
that don't like being touched okay
someone goes to a clinician that's you
know in any intervention is primarily
touch-based doesn't like being touched
uh you might you know might go well you
may synchronize extremely well you know
kind of they understand you they talk
when you start saying okay let's have a
look that's palpate that you can feel
like
there's a there's a fight or flight kind
of mode the person goes in straight away
so i think
understanding this
is also quite important in understanding
the limits of competence of someone
you know in musculoskeletal care for
example that that's an area that where
probably the person needs to be referred
to someone else an expert in the area
maybe
by getting a sense of you know this
there's a response here that's not the
one i would expect
to perhaps
not then to open the pandora box oh
let's tell me a little bit about what's
going on here because again you know
it's a kind of you know you you probably
triggered you pressed on a button
that uh yeah you know keep the lid on
kind of thing don't open it please
because
so
this is important i think both both ways
is it's a kind of the the power as a
therapeutic tool
but also the power of
triggering responses that actually uh
are quite you know
quite important to take into account and
in fact you know it's it's
you know the the paper we got accepted
yesterday which is the continuation of
this musculoskeletal care
you know one of the reviewers actually
wanted us to say
you know there are you know
psychologists
in a psychotherapy treat people that
memories are embodied and you need to be
aware of avoiding overlaps okay
so that means don't jump into an area
that you don't know about
and but be aware that sometimes you know
you yeah you're getting that the
response is pretty much you're getting
into someone
hidden states stuff that is there in the
background
just leave it alone please that's the
way at least i see my you know the world
around me is like
don't don't
don't sort of start the process that you
don't want to or or if you don't if you
do then
go and see someone else
thank you
blue
and then oh sorry ian and then blue
oh it's okay i didn't have my hand up so
over to blue sorry okay blue go for it
so it's interesting um and i don't know
if like in your um
work as an osteopath but like there's
many layers like i found like through
working emotionally physically on myself
through my life like it's like peeling
an onion right and so as you go through
um it's interesting that like
like all this stuff resurfaces and like
even physical trauma remains there like
you stub your pinky toe you stub your
pinky toe 25 times 35 times 255 times
who knows how many times right depends
on how clumsy you are but but your pinky
toe remembers being stubbed
like it has maybe like a hyper response
because it's been stubbed so many times
because it's whatever that's its little
um job in life is to be stubbed i think
um but but
like it's interesting that um
you know you kind of have to open it up
to to do the work and i wonder like what
kind of synchronous work there is like i
mean i know that there are some people
that deal with like
physical and emotional trauma and i know
like physical trauma can be a
manifestation of emotional trauma um and
you can have emotional trauma based on
your physical trauma so again it's like
this like bi-directional circular loop
and
um i i wonder what like the training is
and osteopathy to deal with emotional
trauma that may come up or um
what kind of uh
like are there people that do
integrative practices like you have to
be a
like an osteopath and then maybe you do
your residency as a psychiatrist or what
kind of you know
can you get it all out like if you have
like some kind of linked
problem that's both physical and
emotional
thank you
george thank you
uh okay um
so the so
so the model in terms of
therapeutic alliance and synchrony and
using touch if we use to the whole world
of healthcare practice you know could
argue that
you know in a world of psychotherapy for
example mind-body kind of stuff uh yeah
the person would be
um
sort of um
equipped with the tools to explore to to
enable them to open up to start the
process and being able to deal with that
so so the the paper
has a kind of a generic kind of model
that could apply you know as an umbrella
to a number of areas of practice for
sure we can do that and no problem if we
think specifically about manual therapy
and specifically about osteopathy then
you've got two worlds uh the american
world of osteopathic medicine where
osteopathic medicine is medicine and
you know
the
they are there are osteopaths in the in
the us
who are psychiatrists as well and in
that case yes that person would be
ideally uh suited
to
be able to explore that you know to do
that to kind of uh start a process of
care actually using both their
competences as a psychiatrist and their
competencies as a
you know also manual therapist as a
handle hands-on kind of a practitioner
in other countries um
osteopaths are primarily kind of uh
manual therapists if you want to call it
that way although osteopaths don't like
being called manual therapies but
primarily use manual therapy primarily
uh in musculoskeletal care but you know
other areas of practice
and we start seeing a number of
practitioners going down the route of
like physiotherapists
using
what is called a psychologically
informed
type of practice and that typically
involves some additional training
in counseling or some additional
training in some
you know cvt like kind of approaches
like for example
something like accept acceptance and
commitment therapy for example so stuff
that actually combined with that were
hands-on
is is a sort of
you know
potentiates the effect of the treatment
that the hands-on alone would not
achieve but when you come from the two
kind of two different angles meeting in
the middle and providing a
more robust
package of care
you can get better results
because
you know the training as as a as a
pre-registration level
is very basic uh
to sort of uh to enable you to recognize
that
there are things that um are you know
need a referral to another practitioner
even those that even those that
practice in a psychologically informed
type of practice like
several physiotherapists uh have
developed a kind of a traffic light
system where clearly there are stuff on
on the yellow that
you know anxiety is associated with pain
and so on that's okay you know you can
deal with that there's some stuff
kind of in the in the
in the orange that you have to be a
little bit careful and they clearly
stuff ptsd's and so on uh where you know
it's a no-go zone you know because
you know you you can dive in and then
you don't know if you can come up come
back okay kind of thing okay so that
that is typically a referral to another
practitioner having said that
i think there are opportunities for
collaborative work where
the two together can actually provide a
much better service to a person that
simply relying on one practitioner
that can do everything i think that's
sometimes exploring stuff through the
physical body the import itself
opens the doors
for stuff to be explored at other
elements of the self okay
when the body is a little bit more
prepared to deal with stuff and people
maybe are prepared to talk sometimes you
see that in cases of
childhood abuse and so on you know
kind of had some some stuff that felt
good
some hands-on work even the massage and
the person felt a bit more confident in
themselves and they were prepared then
let's have a child and they were not
prepared to go to talking therapy
straight away because there was
there's too much going on
in there kind of embodied itself
[Music]
the sirens go off
when certain things happen
exactly
ian
yes so um just sort of picking up on the
points from george and the
question from blue um
yeah really totally agree that it's you
know
not the job of a untrained manual
therapist to kind of
aim to
open a can of worms of um something that
you know especially if it's not five
minutes before the end of a session and
then you kind of say okay i want to you
know see you later see you next week and
i've got another client now and you know
that that's not
definitely not not a good idea um
however as you said george sometimes
people will come and they'll want to
offer things and they'll want to talk
about stuff
um
and what i was thinking about blue as
you were asking about sort of the the
different combinations of approaches i
don't know if um
george and zoe or any any of you are
familiar with david bocelli's work on um
tre trauma release or tension release
exercises so
um what
you know he doesn't really go into the
story so it's not kind of
psychoanalytical or
unraveling the stories of people's past
but he has a methods for inducing
kind of
what i think is myofascial and what it
looks like myofascial unwinding so
sometimes it's tremoring um
and um so it's sort of
i don't think he
necessarily uses touch in the beginning
um but it's
i guess what i'm thinking is that there
are ways that if you know the ways of
offering
clients opportunities to
unravel the
bodily
trapped or the the stuff that's held in
the body that um where they don't have
to verbalize it if they don't want to
but the
the in road is to induce some kind of
letting go
um which maybe is what all manual
therapy is about to a greater or lesser
degree but his you know his examples are
quite dramatic you know people will be
making big movements
um
that seemingly are uncontrolled but if
you ask them to stop at any time they
can stop they can bring it into
voluntary but there seems to be a really
big updating of some generative model
through this process um
uh
yeah
they're my thoughts
thank you
um
i'm gonna return to our previous complex
causation network now it's smaller
because we're abstracting away from the
details and think about like
what are some active inference questions
that come to mind and how can we look at
this differently than for example just a
structural equation model that's fit
from many empirical studies and so
here's figure 4.3 from the textbook
and this is a
partially observable markov decision
process
and it's come up in other
papers and live streams so we won't go
into too much details
but the kinds of things that we might
want to ask
are like what variables are latent
states or observable
in general and then in the specific case
for example maybe there's a total
absolutely perfect association between
hippocampus volume and some other
clinical outcome and so hippocampus
volume conceptually is observable it
could be observed but in that exact
patient's case it may not be an
observable in that relationship
so
variables
can be observable in one context and
latent in another context so that might
speak to evidence-based grounding where
like okay we don't know what somebody's
blood level of this is
what's the most informative thing to do
maybe we can measure it and then that
ties their measurements into
other observables so that's one question
what are observables and what are latent
variables
what variables do we have causal
influence on what affordances exist
that might have intervening
influence on some unobserved state so
here's like pi the policy selection
and then
the way that the hidden state is
changing through time
that's what the affordances are about
influencing
the hidden state is the true temperature
of the room the thermometer is the
observed value and then taking an action
like turning on the air conditioning is
about intervening in the hidden state
such that other observables are seen
and then we talked also about like
in what ways can we change the
generative model so here's the policy
selection
of the practitioner
and then in the interface it's like it's
meeting with the observations
of the patient
the actions of the practitioner what
they say and what they do are received
as observations and that's kind of this
dyad active that we've seen so rather
than the one entity navigating and sense
making in the world the joint sense
making
features this interface where the policy
selection's on one and they're thinking
through other minds their inference on
the generative model of the other is
what is being
um
intervened in
how can we change the generative model
the cognitive models
how can we change the generative process
could there be something
welcoming on the door of the room
that is a modification of the niche
or some other design choice that helps
scaffold
this therapeutic niche
and um
yeah what policies can be taken
from the toolkit that is afforded in
that moment based upon the training and
the equipment available and so on
that influence what to result in what
and that kind of comes back to this
synchrony for what
question
just achieving synchrony is like a sort
of
undirected
hypnosis or undirected sort of
i don't know
it's just sort of like this vegetative
propagation of coordination
that
would only coincidentally
be
functional
so having a functional outcome in mind
then there can be a working backwards
like well what observations are we
looking for
and then what hidden states give rise to
those observations and what policies
exist
that intervene in those hidden states
and in the dynamics of how they change
recognizing like their
complexity
so those would just be a few
active inference
variables and approaches that are are
being invoked here
conversationally
however the kinds of models and the
empirical data
to take it
further
are being sketched out
um
well it's going very fast and we're in
kind of the home stretch so what would
anyone like to
look at or turn to
we have a few other questions that
previously had been
raised that we
didn't perhaps
get to
some of them are written here
so anything that people see here that
they're interested in or any other topic
and then also just how are we
coming out of this dot too
what will be different in our action as
we are engaged in this area of course
from many different perspectives george
i i loved your your your kind of
proposal your summary of all the
you know those um those active inference
questions in fact
there's a structure for piper in it
right
uh it can take us down the road even
just sort of looking at some
computational stuff
um so creating some kind of you know
a framework
um
yeah so i i i very much like it
i think there there is a sort of
challenge in what
what are the latents and observables uh
and so on to define those kind of thing
that needs a little bit of thinking um
we can you know
the the other stuff i think you know
as you said you know probably
you know working backwards would sort of
becomes easier you know isn't it you
know if we need kind of
it is about
hands-on with reassurance and you know
and so on if that's a sort of what's you
know the policy and so on and what we
observe
you know
back at the beginning i think you know
it's uh it would be fascinating i think
in terms of
the bio by behavioral kind of element of
synchrony uh there's clearly changes in
them
in breathing changes in
probably heart rate variability and so
on
that would be interesting to
to understand you know is that a sign
that the system is sort of starting
changing um
the process uh
and they talked about the thing in that
you know maybe something in the
the door of the room um
a couple of years ago when i was
practicing in another country um
i i for quite a few months i used to use
a lot of classical music and opera and
so on
and that was
actually a tremendously effective way
of creating an environment where the
person sort of actually a form of
inducing that synchrony
and kind of you know i'm i'm treating
i'm kind of doing this stuff i don't
need to talk that much i'm kind of you
know just
go with the sensations go with the music
and i felt that actually that was a very
good way as a process of start changing
the generative model
um
so there is the the stuff
as we kind of um
proposed on the one of the recent papers
the stuff that you can implement
so if you
doing the tactile the touch-based
intervention and use forms of language
sometimes
to
get the person to visualize what you're
doing you know for example i'm doing
this and i'm trying to achieve that and
you think that the per you know that the
person is
even like interceptively robust enough
to let you explore the
inner sensations to situations as
you know you're probably doing some work
and you you realize
by sort of predicting their internal
states that
they're just focusing too much and
giving too much attention to stuff
which is actually not
not useful
where you can just say oh you know what
uh like we said in the paper you know i
i have a new dog
and i kind of where does the dog come
from but a dog in that sense is a way of
sort of breaking down that
attention to what you're doing to sort
of say oh okay so you you're continuing
you know there's still the sensory
stimulation there is still that sensory
evidence arriving to the system but
actually
you start changing a little bit you know
you
you you're flattening a little bit of
the sensory state by sort of zeroing the
big things and then
maybe those sensations that come in um
potentially kind of change some stuff so
yeah
i think at this level that's for sure
some some stuff
to do i think it's an interesting thing
actually being
started being explored now
with uh
ted kapchuk lab in harvard uh around um
acupuncture which is you know looking at
synchrony as well with hyper scanning
techniques
and kind of finding that actually
successful in terms of the intervention
is associated again what what
synchrony so
kind of uh
it's a body of evidence sort of
building up i think
but nice
one thought on the free energy
minimizing and
ml dawn and several others were
discussing in the chat about like our
biological systems truly finding global
minima and so it's a big question but
just to give one thought on it is
the free energy
is calculated
for a given policy sequence of actions
in terms of how informative
that sequence of actions is expected to
be
and how useful that sequence of action
is supposed to be expected to be
and so
different action
pathways are evaluated based upon their
ability to reduce uncertainty
or provide direct value
and so if we can just maybe there's
multiple things that have value in the
therapeutic alliance but one
um for the generative model of the
practitioner might be like to reduce a
number on a pain survey that would be
useful
and then there might be multiple
policies
and maybe adequacy is good enough
and if the pathways are
to some balance or shifting balance of
informative and useful
either reducing pain or helping
understand how to reduce pain
then navigating and shifting policies
is something that can be done adaptively
and then in contrast the policies that
might want to be disfavored would be
like the ones that are adding confusion
reducing clarity of sense-making or
increasing pain
um and that's not to say that there's
not moments where transiently surprise
does increase or pain does increase
but that is part of a policy like i'm
going to touch this place
that might transiently increase pain but
that might be an informative action that
in a
extended timeline is part of a free
energy minimizing trajectory and so what
is the horizon and so on george and then
anyone else
uh
that thing you know sort of modifying
pain you know modifying symptoms
it's quite an interesting thing because
you know for example at least in my
profession there's this idea that you
know we don't treat the symptoms we
treat the cause of the problem okay
so you know pain is just a symptom it's
nothing to worry about okay
um
but you know from this perspective
actually me you know
changing symptoms reducing symptoms is
actually an important thing quite an
important thing particularly if you
if you're thinking about chronic
conditions if you start making the
person start feeling a little bit better
then you probably start changing the
whole you know the whole process
uh if you don't change anything you know
it's the how is the person going to
engage in that if actually
you know you can continue saying yeah
you know
you're moving much better you know your
function is so much better but actually
the person says you know you know what
but
hasn't reduced at all i'm still in agony
so
so i think you know going a little bit
with small things at that level are
quite important in the greater scheme of
things
in terms of changing the generative
model um
so it it it is clearly you know
a fundamental bit uh of of the jigsaw
and it's the same you know as you said
informing for example you know this
might be uncomfortable but in fact is
important in um
in kind of uh you know achieving
something so the same way some persons
some patients tell you uh it is painful
but it's a good pain so again what's the
value of the good pain is the reward
this is a sort of anticipation that this
will lead to a positive change
thank you zoe
yeah i think george just kind of touched
upon what i was going to say um
pain
you know sometimes patients
i know i have patients that come to a
session and they expect it to be painful
i mean a lot of people expect that at
some point you know it they might get
that um
sort of quote good pain
where they know they almost want to feel
like something's happening and whether
that feedback is kind of pain or
something that's kind of reassuring i
know patients
especially with sort of osteopathic
manipulative um
sort of
treatment they they want the click
if someone manipulates them they they
they come in and go oh i just want you
to click me
and you know the research shows that not
necessarily you need that that sound but
that feedback that they
sort of want
they they kind of want some people they
expect if you do a hard sort of a more
firm massage they feel like they're i
don't know getting a money's worth or
they're getting more sort of treatment
than than
if they want they want you to they kind
of want that feedback to say yeah you're
in the right place
um
and i get that a lot so i think
pain is is an interesting one i think it
just the
the bios synchrony the that we get we go
upon
you know whether it is the patient's
heart rate their breathing changes you
see their facial expression changes when
you're
or the muscle tightens up nearby you
kind of go on on that but
i think it's what they expect to get
from treatment not every patient's gonna
come in and go yeah i wanna
i wanna be in less pain that might not
be their ultimate goal obviously they're
not gonna say no to it but
they might really just want to be able
to pick their kid up or
go to sleep with just being able to go
to sleep not being in pain or not waking
up or
something like that so i think it's not
yes we can clinically
it's not so simple as something that we
can measure imperatively it might be
something
that's you know a goal
to that patient is more important than
you know if their pain is less or if
they're moving better or
oh well yeah you know if we we had the
technology um to say look oh look your
heart rate's lower or this means that
you're more efficient you know you're
saving free energy because you're not
expending on your pain or you know
you're more efficient so it's not gonna
you'll have more energy to to do this
now that you're doing this better they
they may not care they may just want to
be able to pick their kid up um
and not be in pain
so i think
what we're measuring i think will be
very individual to the patient and it
might not be something that
is necessarily useful in terms of
research um
that we can quantify it it just might be
that goal that's not always sort of
empirical
yeah thank you zoe
ian
thanks
thanks all and um yeah just as you were
saying that you know that zoe you said
at the beginning i think the the
intention behind it all is to help them
and i'm just
thinking of a scenarios or some
scenarios of when um
you know agreeing on the goals is so
important so i'm thinking short-term
goals and long-term goals here so
clients who are maybe endurance runners
and you know they want to do
fix ultra-marathons a year and they come
to you because their calves are hurting
so your immediate goal is to reduce the
pain in their calves so they can make
the ultramarathon at the end of the
month
but then you know do i really
if i'm if i'm aware as a therapist that
there's a link between
endurance running and developing
arrhythmias heart arrhythmias for
example and i see this person is very
anxious
about
their goals to the point where you know
it's almost like they need it rather
than it's a
um
a pleasure
as such then
you know if i disagree with their goal
um are we am i true you know and saying
actually maybe four ultra marathons a
year would be enough for you um am i
just enabling
this drive by relieving your calf pain
um in the short term
uh so you know agreeing i think agreeing
on those like longer you know more
broader life goals and
um
or referring to someone else if i don't
agree
with
with that or just so you know
that's a that's a more of an ethical
issue everybody came to mind as we were
talking there
yeah that reminds me of like the kind of
performances that we might see in the
olympics or the medical care that might
happen like on the sideline of a
game where somebody has been injured
but they're gonna like continue doing it
almost
um in a way that is like rapidly
degrading potentially the future weeks
of their health
and then that's the ethical challenge or
the decision-making challenge like is it
is it worth them to hobble across the
finish line
with an injury that every step is it's
just deteriorating the injury
but then
being consistent with a belief
that one is a finisher
or even a signal
to those who are watching there's so
many complex phenomena
at that level
um
those are very
interesting questions
um
wow so
we're towards
the end here i guess for the um authors
and for anyone else we can give some of
our last thoughts what are
some of your next directions
for this line of research and
application
okay so um
well first of all
as uh as last time was a fascinating
discussion i think
and
learning a lot from from this kind of
interaction for sure um
within this we um
sort of got some stuff done in
publishing the musculoskeletal
side of things we
have another paper to be submitted
very soon the next week or so uh the
same topic but in pediatrics and there's
the bulk of other stuff building up
um i think you know what we want to
achieve now is to start
testing some of these ideas kind of
empirically
using different methods
um
from
uh qualitative kind of phenomenological
type of approaches trying to understand
really what's going on
to more
you know sort of um
neural bio
stuff kind of along the lines of
looking at for example
some
some markers of by behavioral synchrony
like
for example um
you know
physiological changes in both the
practitioner
and
and the patient
bearing in mind some of this stuff
it is a bit more challenging to achieve
because
uh whereas for example in the in the
field of psychotherapy the person
practitioner is typically sitting down
uh the guy doing manual therapies prob
you know he's moving around so therefore
the heart rate's not going to be exactly
the same but you know looking at what's
what can be done um
and uh
and you know and some you know creating
some some
some some models as well so the idea
around
computational stuff also makes sense you
know
to test
um
some of the ideas
uh this is work that is building up so
you know we
very much look forward to kind of people
getting in touch um
bouncing off ideas from each other kind
of uh
uh looking at how we can move forward
with this there's
it's not osteopathic specific is is more
than that i think at least
it can be
manual therapy
you know more broadening along those
lines uh he can look at uh
sort of uh you know the role of some of
this stuff in chronic conditions
not just pain but you know other other
persistent physical symptoms uh
and so on so that's that's where we are
it's time now to start kind of
testing some of the stuff for sure and
stop writing theoretical tapes
cool um
zoey
yeah um sort of
what george said um we've got
i've got um
we've had one paper accepted for
um msk so hopefully that will come out
for
everyone to read soon
we've got one
waiting
um
okay
so um for more orthopedic um
general yeah musculoskeletal muscle in
um
muscle and bones kind of um
patients
and then um the pediatrics one is almost
ready to submit um
and then yeah i guess we'll be looking
towards seeing where it goes and and
what we can sort of empirically
prove from all the theories that are
kind of circulating um
and going
and going from there but
hopefully discussions like what
everyone said now will give everyone
more ideas to sort of
where we're
where we're going or where we could go
and different ways to apply
the
um principles and the frameworks that
we've suggested so far
awesome george uh yeah just you know on
on the pediatrics uh we actually have
you know one of the first lines to start
exploring is is uh synchrony between
mother baby and practitioner um
starting with um
not sure if we're gonna we've been done
you know we've been doing a
a bit of work around you know the effect
of touch on premature babies um so we
have those collaborations with hospitals
in italy will not enable us to do some
of that stuff but we we sort of start
looking also
you know looking at this whole concept
of of synchrony uh
on a triadic kind of thing so the baby
the practitioner and the mother and see
if actually if we find that
you know the synchrony actually between
mother and baby is a marker of you know
for example the baby would be you know
some some some
some markers of um you know autonomic
change you know changes in autonomic
arousal for example like we observed for
example the effect of effective touch
uh gentle touch on the baby
thank you ian
uh george just as you were saying about
the challenge of um a practitioner being
moving
whilst during the you know manual
therapy session and yeah i'm sort of
aware of
how that does
lead to some difficulties
especially with the ppg sort of
measurement of heart rate variability um
i heard just an idea i heard about uh i
don't know don't know if you've come
across it and he see a wearable ecg
that um
incur it's aimed at increasing
respiratory sinus arrhythmia it
stimulates it vibrates and it stimulates
the person catches them at the top of
their out breath
and it's designed to actually be used
whilst you're walking around
in everyday life
so i'm just wondering if there's an
opportunity there to
um
because it's designed to
a
increase rsa and b
to be used whilst moving that might be
an interesting piece of kit to use
yeah absolutely
cool
blue
or would anyone else like any comments
um i just want to give a final thought
so something that i'm going to be
thinking about for
i don't know whoever knows how long um
is this idea of um
the emotional and physical
body
in terms of reference point
right so we we studied in i think live
stream 40 the um fep for generic quantum
systems and
it it
talked about how
like the fep drives entanglement
um
and
in this way like when there's when
there's perfect learning there's like
this overlapping of the reference point
so i just wonder like how like can an
emotional body and a physical body be
driven toward a more overlapping
reference frame like when those things
are so
fundamentally different um so i'm going
to be thinking about that
cool
very cool
all right well
thank you for this excellence
dot two that
concludes
and
really appreciated the authors joining
and blue thank you for joining ian also
for
contributing so much with the dot zero
and
everyone is welcome back to give us
updates on their learning and
application on this very important area
so thanks again everybody see you later
thank you thank you
goodbye
you